Samuel Adams Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Samuel Adams Papers 1635-1826
MSS10223
Adams, Samuel, 1722-1803
2,500 items 19 containers 3.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Continental congressman and governor of Massachusetts. Reproductions of correspondence, speeches, petitions, committee records, and other material relating primarily to Adams’s political life in Massachusetts.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Adams, John, 1735-1826--Correspondence.; Adams, Samuel, 1722-1803.; Burgoyne, John, 1722-1792--Correspondence.; Gadsden, Christopher, 1724-1805--Correspondence.; Gates, Horatio, 1728-1806--Correspondence.; Gerry, Elbridge, 1744-1814--Correspondence.; Greene, Nathanael, 1742-1786--Correspondence.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826--Correspondence.; Lee, Arthur, 1740-1792--Correspondence.; Lee, Richard Henry, 1732-1794--Correspondence.; Paine, Thomas, 1737-1809--Correspondence.; Warren, James, 1726-1808--Correspondence.
Places
Massachusetts--Politics and government--18th century.
Occupations
Delegates, U.S. Continental Congress--Massachusetts.; Governors--Massachusetts.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Samuel Adams, continental congressman and governor of Massachusetts, were given to the Library of Congress by James B. Wilbur in 1926.
Other Repositories
The originals of this collection are held by the New York Public Library, New York, N.Y.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Samuel Adams are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site, and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1722, Sept. 27 Born, Boston, Mass.
1740 Graduated, Harvard College, Cambridge, Mass.
1743 M.A., Harvard College, Cambridge, Mass.
1756-1764 Brewer and tax collector, Boston, Mass.
1765-1774 Member, Massachusetts general court
1774-1781 Member, Continental Congress
1776 Signer of the Declaration of Independence
1779 Member, Massachusetts state constitutional convention
1781 President, Massachusetts state senate
1788 Member, Massachusetts state constitutional convention Unsuccessful candidate for election to the first U.S. Congress
1789-1794 Lieutenant governor of Massachusetts
1794-1797 Governor of Massachusetts
1803, Oct. 2 Died, Boston, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Samuel Adams (1722-1803) span the years 1635-1826 and consist of reproductions of originals in the New York Public Library documenting Adams’s political career in Massachusetts and some family matters. Included is correspondence, speeches, petitions, committee records, public documents relating to Massachusetts, and pseudonymous articles submitted to Boston newspapers and attributed to Samuel Adams. A considerable amount of material does not pertain directly to Adams, either as writer or recipient.
Notable correspondents or individuals represented in the collection include John Adams, John Burgoyne, Christopher Gadsden, Horatio Gates, Elbridge Gerry, Nathanael Greene, Thomas Jefferson, Arthur Lee, Richard Henry Lee, Thomas Paine, and James Warren.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged chronologically.
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm81010223
Container List
- 1635, Oct.-1769, Feb. 1 (Box 1)
- 1769, Feb. 13-1770, Dec. 31 (Box 2)
- 1771, Jan. 1-1773, Feb. 15 (Box 3)
- 1773, Jan. 6-1774, Jan. 8 (Box 4)
- 1774, Jan. 25-June 6 (Box 5)
- 1774, June 30-1775, Jan. 19 (Box 6)
- 1775, Jan. 29-Dec. 9 (Box 7)
- 1775, Dec. 19-1776, May 31 (Box 8)
- 1776, June 2-Dec. 31 (Box 9)
- 1777, Jan. 1-Dec. 22 (Box 10)
- 1778, Jan. 1-Aug. 25 (Box 11)
- 1778, Sept. 1-1779, Mar. 31 (Box 12)
- 1779, Apr. 1-Dec. 24 (Box 13)
- 1780, Jan. 4-Dec. 31 (Box 14)
- 1781, Jan. 8-1782, Nov. 21 (Box 15)
- 1783, Jan. 29-Dec. 22 (Box 16)
- 1784, Jan. 30-1787, Dec. 3 (Box 17)
- 1788, June 5-1793, Nov. 30 (Box 18)
- 1794, Jan, 17-1826, Jan.9, undated (Box 19)